Guide to the Roberson Family Papers, 1917-1977
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Roberson family papers 1917-1977
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Roberson family
3.0 linear feet Extent: 2250 Items
Cecil F. and Marie Roberson were Southern Baptist missionaries in Nigeria between the 1950s and 1970s. Collection consists largely of historical essays and archives written and collected by Cecil Roberson to document the history of Baptists in Nigeria. Roberson's own writings are complemented by photocopies and reproductions of the Thomas Jefferson Bowen and Lurana Henrietta Davis Bowen Papers, as well as a series of correspondence written to and from Louis M. Duval between 1917 and 1934. This collection is part of the Nigerian Southern Baptist Missionary Collection held at the Rubenstein Library.
RL.01109
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Roberson Family Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2013.
Historical Note
Cecil F. and Marie Roberson were Southern Baptist missionaries in Nigeria between the 1950s and 1970s.
Collection Overview
Collection consists largely of historical essays and archives written and collected by Cecil Roberson to document the history of Baptists in Nigeria. Roberson's own history writings are complemented by photocopies and reproductions of the Thomas Jefferson Bowen and Lurana Henrietta Davis Bowen Papers, as well as a series of correspondence written to and from Louis M. Duval between 1917 and 1934.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Roberson, Cecil F.; Roberson, Marie; Bowen, T.J. (Thomas Jefferson), 1814-1875; Duval, Louis M.; Southern Baptist Convention. Foreign Missions Board; Nigeria -- Description and travel; Missionaries -- Nigeria; Married people in missionary work; Lagos -- Description and travel; Oyo (Nigeria) -- Description and travel
Contents of Collection
- Roberson's History Writings, 1950s-1970s, (3 boxes)
  A series of research essays, notes, and writings created by Cecil Roberson recounting the history of various Baptist missionary projects in Nigeria and Lagos. A subseries, The Papers by Cecil Roberson, represent the Robersons' arrangement of the materials prior to their arrival at the Rubenstein Library.
  - "A Chronology of the Baptists in Nigeria, West Africa, and Related Subjects", (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Cliff Lewis manuscript of Bowen Letters and Cecil Roberson's Bowen biography (Box 2)
  - "The Story of Buguma Baptists" and "A History of the Baptist of Oyo, Nigeria, 1856 to 1925," by Cecil Roberson (Box 2)
  - "A History of Baptists in Nigeria, 1849-1935," by Cecil Roberson, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - "Bowen, or an Evidence of Grace," and "Egunleti, Second Bada of Shaki: Farmer, Warrior, and Exemplary Christian," by Cecil Roberson (Box 2)
  - Papers by Cecil Roberson
    - Bibliography (Box 2)
    - "A History of Lagos Baptists," undated (Box 2)
    - "How to Build a Mud House in Mississippi," 1979, and "The Baptist Property, Ago Ijaiye, Abeokuta," undated (Box 2)
    - "Speech Delivered before the Ede General Workers' Confederence, 8th Feb. 1963" and "Some Errors in the Brochure 'A Short History of the Ebenezer Baptist Church,'" undated (Box 2)
    - "Batonu Children Learn to Pray," and "Some Points Relative to the Legal Status of the Baptist Mission and Its Missionaries," 1965 (Box 3)
      Includes a letter from Cecil Robinson regarding an archival collection of Nigerian Baptist missionary materials, 1966.
    - "Criticism of Proposed Joint Proprietorship of the Baptist Press Between the Foreign Mission Board and the Nigerian Baptist Convention," undated; "My Work in Nigeria," undated; "Nigerian Baptist Communion," 1963; "Historical Development in the Field of Education in the Baptist Mission-Nigeria," undated (Box 3)
    - "Church and State Relations," 1957; "Some Suggestions Relative to Mission Organization and Strategy," 1963; "Transition," 1963 (Box 3)
    - "Baptist Academy Founder's Day Address," 1962; "My Answers to Questions on Nigerian Mission Work," 1962; "Some Lessons from Baptist History in Nigeria," 1963 (Box 3)
    - "Nigerian Baptist Theological Seminary," undated; "Notes on History of the Qtun Gbede Baptist Church," undated; "Baptist Evangelism in Nigeria," 1968; "Pastors and Leaders/Locations of Buildings Used for Services by the First Baptist Church, Lagos," 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - "100th Anniversary of the First Baptist Church, Lagos," undated; "Life Sketch of Rev. I. A. Adejunmobi," 1963; list of subjects for the Nigerian Baptist History Column; "The Idere Incident, 1908-1913," undated (Box 3)
    - "How to Play the African Game Ayo," undated; "Land Notes-Abeskuta," undated; "Brief History of the Baptist People of Nigeria," 1954; "God's Preparation for Missions in Nigeria," undated (Box 3)
    - "Pin-point Focus on the Origin of the Yoruba Mission," 1964; "Historical Inserts," 1966; "Let These Historical Things Abide," 1955; "Brief Study of Discipline in the Nigerian Baptist Mission," undated; "Story of a Picture," undated (Box 3)
    - "Baptist Involvement in the Treatment of Leprosy in Nigeria," undated; "Report on Materials Collected for Baptist Foreign Mission Board from the estate of Dr. and Mrs. J. B. Rice," 1953; "Points Relative Directly to Production of a History of Baptists in Nigeria," undated; "Nigerian Baptist Theological Seminary Library," undated (Box 3)
    - "Biographical Notes on Rev. Isaac Adekuule Adejunmobi," 1977; "A Missionary Loan to the Foreign Mission Board," undated; "Baptist Female Education Until 1910," 1965; "Origin of the First Baptist Church, Ede," undated (Box 3)
    - "Moses Ladejo Stone," undated and 1955; "Some Observations on the Ministerial Career of Rev. Moses Ladejo Stone," 1966; "The Nigerian Baptist," undated; "The Dawn (Imole Owuro)," undated; "The Nigerian Baptist Women's Missionary Union," undated (Box 3)
    - "Nigerian Baptist Convention," undated; "Yoruba Baptist Association," undated; "First Native Workers' Conference," undated; "Workers' Institute," undated; "Missionary Experiences," undated (Box 3)
  - Minutes of the Nigerian Baptist Convention, 1978 (Box 3)
- The Bowen Papers, (1.5 boxes)
  Research and preparatory materials collected and created by the Robersons about the Rev. Thomas Jefferson Bowen and his wife, Lurana Henrietta Davis Bowen; also includes research papers written by others (unnamed) in honor of the Robersons.
  - Preparatory Materials for the Bowen Papers, Volume II, compiled by the Robersons (Box 3)
  - Ah, Africa: The Letters of Lurana and Thomas Jefferson Bowen, 1849-1875, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - The Bowen Papers: A Compilation of the Papers of Rev. Thomas Jefferson Bowen and his wife Lurana Henrietta (Davis) Bowen, compiled by the Robersons, 1953-1959, (3 folders) (Box 4)
- Louis M. Duval Correspondence, 1917-1934, (4 folders)
  Photocopies and reproductions of correspondence to and from Louis M. Duval, a missionary from St. John, New Brunswick, Canada, who served in Oyo, Nigeria, in the early twentieth century.
  - Correspondence, 1917-1934 and undated, (4 folders) (Box 4)